this episode is brought to you by the
new gold silver vault app get it for
free at hidden secrets of money calm the
entire world is facing a debt driven
disaster the scale of which has never
been seen before in human history the
situation is now so severe that we're
left with only two options default on
our debt or inflate it away you can
already hear people blaming the free
markets and even money itself for our
problems and to me this is just tragic
because we don't have free markets
anymore and we certainly don't use real
life this is the real reason for our
problem our money itself has been
corrupted it's not just an issue of
economics this affects your freedom when
this crisis hits people will be
screaming for the government to do
something when it was the government
that caused the problems in the first
place many societies of face this
dilemma in the past and we can learn
what the outcomes might be simply by
studying what they did and comparing it
to what we are doing today so while I
was in Germany I decided to stop by one
of my favorite museums and take you on a
kind of crash course of the history of
real money how it evolved and the twin
dangers that arise when money is
corrupted I'm here at the Bundesbank
money museum in Germany and this is one
of the best museums I have ever seen
right at the very beginning of the
museum you walk in and it starts with
Bartok you know originally the first
form of currency was livestock the
problem with livestock though like for
instance this town if I traded discount
to you for something and somebody else
wants to trade you something else that's
of much lower value you can't make
change a system that relies on barter is
very inefficient because you not only
suffer from the problems of divisibility
you also rely on the hope that you will
find someone who has a good or service
that you need who wants something that
you have at the same place and at the
same time in economics this is called
the coincidence
once now had the fact that most Goods
have a shelf life before they perish and
you can see why barter systems held
mankind back for so long so what was it
that solved the coincidence of once and
propelled us out of the Stone Age and
into space it was the invention of money
money is not evil it is a magnificent
tool that allows us to trade our
specialized skills and to store our
economic energy without it we'd be
struggling to feed ourselves each day
and our average lifespan would still be
30 in episode one we learned that real
money has to fulfill certain properties
in order to function the 2600 years
after its emergence people still confuse
money with currency even the so called
experts so they've got here some of the
things about what money is the first
example here is money is whatever goes
so in earlier cultures commodities such
as cattle stones or metals were used as
money buyers took the value of the goods
on trust when making their purchase
today - money is a question of
confidence so the currency today isn't
money today we're using currency but the
only reason it has any purchasing power
whatsoever is because yesterday your
experience was that it purchased
something so you have faith that it's
going to purchase something tomorrow
otherwise it has no value whatever form
it takes reliable money has two
characteristics it is genuine and it is
stable people can rely on its value well
you know what fiat currency around the
planet has maintained its value they all
fall in value so right away you can see
the difference they're talking about
currency here and when they say it's
genuine I mean what is genuine a
counterfeit somebody that's running
their own printing press in their
basement is making genuine notes as far
as he's concerned that they're genuine
counterfeit
these things that just come off of a
printing press well yeah it's a genuine
line from a central bank or a government
that you've got something that's going
to store value for you because it
doesn't over long periods of time it
loses value Gold banknotes and
electronic money meaning electronic
currency may be stored divided up or
transported as it's material value has
declined over time
it's genuineness has had to be beyond
question well this one says that it's
got to maintain its value and right here
they're contradicting the next one the
one thing here gold is the only thing
that they're talking about that has not
lost its value in the past where goods
were used as money today
central banks must ensure that the
supply of money is restricted well what
are they doing all over the planet today
they're lifting all the restrictions on
how much currency they're creating
they're flooding the planet with
currency the next display shows the
usual museum pieces that are described
as commodity money cowrie shells
representative axes cocoa beans and the
like well these work better than barter
none of them were actually money because
they all had a weakness one or more
properties of money that they couldn't
fulfill therefore they are commodity
currencies not money some of these were
widely used right up until the beginning
of the 20th century and there's some
stuff here that I haven't seen here's
something very interesting
this brick of tea its value is in the
intrinsic it's in the commodity that
you're using it's the tea but this one
has a certain fungibility to it each
unit would have the same value and you
can make change you can snap these
things apart into units of six it's
portable it's not that heavy this
fulfils quite a few of the functions of
money I would not imagine that it's that
durable it probably doesn't wear that
well and now we come to the emergence of
real money here we have little pieces of
metal just little pieces that have been
Okin off of bars or something that was
cast other little blobs of metal that
were traded as a currency
you know the head purchasing power they
had an intrinsic value but they still
weren't fungible which means
interchangeable every one of them had a
different value you can see that some of
them have a higher silver content some
of them have a higher gold content these
are called electrum it's a mixture of
gold and silver naturally-occurring what
you notice is that this is from the
seventh century BC and then between the
7th and the 6th century we're talking
about somewhere between six eighty and
630 D see the emergence of true money
here we've got four coins the large one
is a one-third stater coin and the other
three are one-sixth stater coins each
unit is interchangeable you can get now
a unit of account you can take so many
of these in trade for so many of loaves
of bread and you don't have to get break
out your little scale and weigh them any
longer with the little chunks of metal
you had to weigh every transaction that
was going on you had to weigh whatever
your payment was and then take a guess
as to what the purity was here you have
some standards that were set by mints
and guaranteed by those mints
these are a unit of account they're
fungible every one of them is
interchangeable they're portable they're
durable in your pocket over long periods
of time they're divisible you can make
change you can see there's a 1/3 stator
and 1/6 skaters and they're a store of
value over long periods of time these
still have purchasing power today 2600
years after they were made another thing
that I find really interesting is
between maybe 680 BC and 300 BC cultures
all around the world they all gravitated
toward gold and silver coinage as money
the entire world sort of decided all
together that gold and silver were money
why because the free markets keep on
selecting gold and silver as money
because of the properties that it has
so now we get to the room of real money
this is a vault door and this is where
they've got all the great examples of
the real gold and silver coins so come
on in and join me so here we get to the
first this is gold and silver what
they're using to make money and here we
have some very early representations of
gold and silver coins and I love these
displays they start with coins and Lydia
so these coins go back to the very first
minting of true coinage so here we have
the starting of the sixth century BC and
then it goes up to the third century and
then from the fifth to the 11th century
and the 13th to the 15th century and
these displays just go on and on with
the history of of real money gold and
silver here are 17th and 18th century
here we come to the 19th century
and now we're all the way up to the 20th
century here and here we come to our
first example of government-issued fiat
currency this is from China this is from
1375 and what's interesting is I have a
chart that compares the value of the
paper currency in China compared to
silver and there was a hyperinflation of
this currency it wasn't backed by
anything it wasn't backed by taxes it
wasn't backed by anything in the
Treasury they could just print this and
so this went into a hyperinflation
because the government was just running
its budget by just doing deficit
spending by printing and then I'm going
to skip to some of the colonial currency
this is the United States and each one
of these currencies is printed by a
different state we've got Maryland South
Carolina North Carolina Connecticut New
York this one here is particularly
interesting it's printed in 14th year of
the reign of King George V 3rd it's
dated March 25th 1776 so this is just a
few months before the Declaration of
Independence
it says his death to counterfeit but
this was printed just before we started
coming out with the Continental dollar
which went into a hyperinflation because
of pure deficit spending on the
Revolutionary War and so this is the
wall where real money gets corrupted
this is where it all turns to paper
which sometimes is backed by something
but it can be a lie they can print more
than they have of the stuff to back it
as we learned in Episode two one of the
first things the country does at the
outbreak of war is to suspend Redemption
rights so that their currency is no
longer redeemable in gold this is
exactly what Germany did before World
War one after losing the war they
suffered through one of the worst
hyperinflations on record when they were
burdened with massive reparation
payments to France and the Allies these
heavy penalties stifled the German
economy and brought it to a standstill
leaving the country with the same two
choices all indebted nations have faced
throughout history default on their debt
or inflated away defaulting was not a
viable option as they were completely
impoverished weakened and surrounded by
armed forces ready to take their land
since their currency was no longer tied
to gold it was decided to light up the
printing presses and inflate their way
out paying the debts with new currency
created out of thin air
this had drastic consequences check out
some of this whymark currency the
display starts with one mark that
actually purchased something that soon
the notes rise to the thousands then the
millions then the billions and finally
the trillions it's mind-blowing
you'll notice that I'm laughing a little
bit as we move through the museum but
I'm not laughing at the people I'm
laughing at the stupidity of central
banks and of governments and how we
never seem to learn from history okay
and this is an example of different
currencies used during the
hyperinflation and they call some of it
inflation money and emergency money this
is interesting they figured the way out
of hyperinflation was to print more so
in 1923 the value of money fell by 50%
or more per day so that means prices are
doubling every day it's falling by 50%
nearly everyone spent their money as
quickly as possible on bread shares and
other safe assets well I don't consider
shares safe assets actually the stock
market did not keep up with the
inflation however this rapid circulation
only served to stoke inflation even
further that's the function of velocity
of money it's just a wind velocity
except it's just like expanding the
quantities have the same effect at the
end even 144 printing companies working
for the rice bank could not keep up with
advanced or banknotes emergency money
issued by city's local authorities as
well as banks and other enterprises
started being circulated so everybody
was issuing currency to add to the
currency that the government was
printing like crazy
although bank notes with face values of
trillions of marks were issued the vast
demand from for money that's not correct
the vast demand for currency led to a
paper shortage printers use anything
that could be found including wool wood
and silk so here's some example of wood
wool and silk currency dollar here so
and this is a great example of how even
here in a Museum of what they call money
this is the Bundesbank
one of the world's great central banks
if you can call any central bank correct
they don't understand the difference
between money and currency they're
calling all of this money and has
nothing to do with money this is just a
promise it was a promise to pay money at
one point and then it was a broken
promise people will have faith in these
government created currencies and it
allows that government to basically rob
their own people the government erased
the debts of that they had left over in
from World War one by just hyper
inflating the currency and basically
that transfers all the wealth of the
middle class to the government the
government inflated away the debts but
they also inflate away the prosperity of
their entire population
when we were in Germany we got a chance
to shoot in front of the Bundestag which
used to be called the Reichstag and it
felt it's very very significant in that
out of monetary crisis you very often
see the political landscape change
dramatically it's the middle class of
the country that defines the country
with their vote they're the largest
sector of any country about 70% and a
currency crisis like a hyperinflation
wipes out and impoverishes the middle
class and they become filled with fear
and it's very easy for somebody to come
in and prey on that fear and dictators
arise out of hyperinflation and this is
one of my greatest fears as far as the
United States goes I think that you know
we all have to be very very careful and
very watchful for what happens in the
future
a few years ago I was interviewing
congressman Ron Paul and he said I think
that there's going to be a financial
collapse before they come around to
thinking seriously about monetary policy
but the real thing we have to worry
about is not the loss of our well it's
the rise of a dictator it's the loss of
our freedom and what's interesting is
the rise of Hitler there were two times
where he played on the public sphere he
could never have come to power had there
not been a hyperinflation back in 1923
just one week before the end of that
hyperinflation that's when Hitler made
his first big public appearance playing
to the public fear Hitler and his
stormtroopers took over a beer hall
called the Burger brow Keller seats
around 3,000 people and he took the
stage by gunpoint into this literally
captive audience he gave the speech that
would change the world because of the
hyperinflation the audience had been
recently impoverished their wealth had
been stolen by the government running
the printing presses and so they're all
scared he offers them a scapegoat and
tells them he's got the way out he
became very popular after that and the
very next day the people that were
listening to him followed him in an
attempt to overthrow the government
he was arrested tried and convicted of
high treason and served time while he
was in jail he was provided with a
private secretary Rudolf Hess and he
actually wrote about half of mine comp
while he was serving time but once the
economy started to recover Hitler lost
that leverage that power he could no
longer play on the fear of the public
once the economic situation had changed
by the middle of the Roaring Twenties he
had become a joke the Nazi Party had
gone to less than 2% of the vote then
along came the Great Depression and
Hitler seized this opportunity again
he was the first politician to actually
campaign by aircraft hitting multiple
cities in a single day and the Nazi
Party went from 2% of the vote to the
second largest party in Germany so
playing on the public sphere Hitler was
able to take away the rights of German
he was able to all these guaranteed
rights in the Bymark Constitution
private property rights the right to
assemble public assembly the right to
privacy in the mail the telephone system
he just took away all of their rights
and seized power so these are the some
some of the things that we have to be
concerned about and be very mindful of
economic crisis very often leads to the
rise of the dictators yeah the fact that
this was just 70 to 80 years ago
basically there are still people alive
today that experienced this but enough
of them have died off to where the
warnings fall on deaf ears Berlin is a
great example of another massive danger
to individual freedom that economic
crisis can bring the swing from
capitalism to collectivism after World
War 2 the city was basically divided in
half the West being capitalist and the
East Communist Germany was reunified in
1990 but even this short period of
separation showed the vastly different
levels of prosperity that the two
systems achieved so this is the famous
checkpoint charlie and what's
interesting is how quickly an economy
can heal just twenty years ago you would
have seen a tremendous difference
between the East and the West you'd have
one side that has tall buildings and is
much more industrialized and new and
then one side that was that's very old
and gray it was one of the best examples
of what a state-run society does to an
economy how the more the public relies
on government the worse the general
economy gets what happens you know in
capitalism you have the greatest
disparity between the poorest and the
richest individuals and there's a
backlash against that and you see this
happening it happened in waves and
cycles this cycle that goes from
capitalism to collectivism here the
example I mean you had this line going
right through a city and one side of the
city that was very poor and the other
side prosperous by
now when we go toward collectivism they
want to eliminate this great disparity
between the poorest and the richest
individuals but what happens isn't that
they raise the standard of living for
the poor up here they drag the whole
economy down so that everybody ends up
living down here except for the people
that are in running the government
collectivism is a danger because we've
proven time and time again that it
doesn't work the evidence is in if you
look at history it's clear that maximum
prosperity can only be achieved through
individual freedom free markets and
sound money you'd think that we've
learned from history but I'm going to
show you a few more displays from the
museum that proved conclusively we
haven't and this is where we are today
this is a sheet of 50 euro notes and
they've come out of the printing press
Bam Bam Bam Bam Bam just like those no
it's good and the entire world today is
sort of every Central Bank across the
planet who's creating currency like
crazy right now
- I think we're going into a deflation
so they're trying to stave off deflation
right now by printing their way out of
it so here we've got some examples of
the technology that governments around
the world are putting into their
counterfeit currency so the public can't
counterfeit the currency that the
government's are now counterfeiting so
you've got all these Holograms and
watermarks and different threads and
different types of paper and then here's
this big old printing plate where they
pop these things out a mile a minute and
right now they are hyper inflating the
base money around the world the paper
money we're going into a deflation
though if the credit money the zune do
hocus-pocus currency that the bank's
just typed into the computer that's
starting to collapse where this stuff is
expanding
so we learned an episode for the modern
currency creation is a complete scam but
a whole lot of people had trouble
believing that it could be true the
European Central Bank has this awesome
display that shows you exactly how it's
done and it's basically the same as our
episode four so here's a quick recap
thanks to the ECB basically the central
bank and the treasury swap io u--'s the
bank rate the central bank writes a
check and the Treasury issues a Treasury
bond which is an IOU and that creates
currency and then it gets somebody who's
paid it gets deposited into a bank
account and a thousand marks
they would hold 10% so right here
they're already telling you that his
bank account is a lie he put a deposit
of 200 it deposited a thousand in it
they only withhold 100 in case he wants
some of that and then they loan out 900
which then they she buys something from
this guy he deposits the 900 they
borrowed 90% of that and leave just 10%
on deposit for him and the result is
that it expands every thousand ends up
creating 10,000 for every $1 creates $10
it you know they've got the results here
it's all sort of a voodoo hocus-pocus of
scheme one of the great things that I've
noticed here is that throughout the
museum they keep on proving the point
that even though this is the Bundesbank
museum they prove the point that fiat
currencies that come off of a printing
press eventually go to zero that they're
really worthless this says the ideal
goal of all monetary systems was to
ensure that money is trustworthy and
kept in short supply metal based
currencies restrict the money supply
because metal deposits are naturally
limited however during the industrial
revolution in the 19th century the
rapidly growing economy needed a means
of payment which could adapt flexibly to
this growth so
Loney you can have a fixed currency
supply and when you have economic growth
it means that the currency gains in
purchasing power in the 20th century
uncovered currencies meeting unpacked
currencies have been the norm in
principle the money stock could grow
unchecked this is why central banks must
ensure that the money stock is in line
with economic growth yeah right so here
we've got my buddy Milton actually
Milton was sort of a semi free-market
economist he won the Nobel Prize
so he's considered the Dean of the
Chicago School of monetary thought which
are monetarist they believe that we
should have a Federal Reserve and it
should expand and contract the currency
supply to achieve the stable prices one
of the problems with Keynesian
monetarists and so on is that they think
you should expand it and contract it but
they never contracted like just you know
Keynesian you're supposed to spend when
the economy is bad the government's
supposed to spend and stimulate and then
withdraw currency from circulation to
keep us from going into a bubble caused
by the expansion of credit and the
spending that they did during the dead
portion of the economy so they take this
rubber band and they stretch it and it's
supposed to come back but they never do
that they just keep on stretching it to
infinity and here we are right now where
we are in the world is that that rubber
band is about to snap with every
currency on the planet and so I'm
instability on a deflation inflation let
me see I'm going to cause a
hyperinflation up it just went off the
inflation scale I guess I did cause a
hyperinflation oops
[Music]
and now the whole thing is collapsing
this game of inflation and deflation has
never worked right now we're on the
precipice of the whole system collapsing
and just like the game our monetary
system will reset this is where the twin
dangers we learned about may rear their
ugly heads so it's up to all of us to
learn from history I mentioned earlier
that it was the invention of money that
allowed humans to prosper and rise out
of the Stone Age but money is only part
of the equation what uses money if you
don't have freedom so what's going to
happen will we default or inflate our
way out of the mess we're in
since 2005 I've been stating publicly
and I also wrote in my book that I
believe we're headed toward a series of
events involving a short-term deflation
followed by a big inflation or
hyperinflation if you really want to
learn how this inflation might affect
you and your family join me at hidden
secrets of money comm for this episode's
exclusive presentation it's a special
video that shows where I believe we are
on this economic rollercoaster of a ride
and how I think it will play out so for
now what can you do 1 share this video
on social media and subscribe to our
YouTube channel to educate yourself by
watching the rest of this series and 3
take action to protect yourself and your
family
learn what you can do at hidden secrets
of money calm I'll see you there
should I buy a half million or a million
let me see how much this is not going to
travel well in the suitcase but it would
be good to have a million euros wouldn't
it tough decisions so okay I'm going to
buy a quarter million euros so here's 50
euros for your quarter million and yeah
and I get changed back about eight euros
to buy a quarter million euro okay okay
and what's interesting is these are
going to eventually be in here and it
won't be too long before these end up
like this oh and we get some chocolate
gold coin danke Schoen
[Music]
so that's our tour of one of the best
monetary museums I've seen so far but
what amazes me is that they still just
don't get it
[Music]
this episode was brought to you by the
new gold silver vault app get the latest
silver and gold prices news videos and
track your holdings using the virtual
vault feature all in the palm of your
hand get it for free at hidden secrets
of money calm